Groups Against Smelter Pollution (G.A.S.P.) records, 1984-1987
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Groups Against Smelter Pollution (G.A.S.P.) records 1984-1987
MS 402
Groups Against Smelter Pollution (G.A.S.P.)
Records, 1984-1986. This collection is composed of the records of Groups Against Smelter Pollution (G.A.S.P.), including: administrative files; activity files; communication files; correspondence; newspaper clippings; negatives, photographs, and slides; and one scrapbook. Also includes research materials compiled by G.A.S.P., regarding the Phelps Dodge Corporation as well as other topics of interest to this environmental coalition.
8 Linear Feet (about 9,300 items)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Historical Note
Groups Against Smelter Pollution (G.A.S.P.) was founded in 1984 by a group of concerned citizens who sought to minimize smelter pollution in Southeastern Arizona and Northern Sonora for the preservation of human health, the environment, and the economy. Acting upon their mission, Groups Against Smelter Pollution organized to educate themselves and others about what they referred to as the "Grey Triangle," an area formed by three smelters: the Phelps Dodge Smelter in Douglas, Arizona, the Compania Minera de Cananea smelter in Cananea, Sonora, and the Mexican de Cobre Smelter in Nacozari, Sonora. G.A.S.P. focused on education, outreach and direct action: publishing newsletters, organizing protests, circulating petitions and instigating letter writing campaigns throughout their three years of operation. With the majority of G.A.S.P. membership located in the Bisbee/Douglas area, group members focused their activism on compelling public officials to force Phelps Dodge Corporation to meet the federal air pollution standards of the Clean Air Act by July 16, 1986 or shut down the Douglas Reduction Works. G.A.S.P. members were also active in documenting the health and environmental effects smelter pollution was having on themselves, their families, and their communities through photographs and testimonials. In 1986, G.A.S.P. put intense pressure on the Environmental Protection Agency to deny Phelps Dodge Corporation the Nonferrous Smelter Order that would allow the smelter to continue operating with no restrictions. In July of 1986 the Environmental Protection Agency refused to renew a suspension of the exemption from state smokestack emissions limits. Phelps Dodge closed the smelter on January 15, 1987. G.A.S.P. disbanded shortly thereafter.
Organization
This collection is organized into eight series. Four series contain subseries: Administrative Files, Activity Files, Phelps Dodge Files, and Subject Files.
Series I: Administrative Files, 1984-1987
Subseries:Organizational History, 1985
Subseries:Financial Files, 1984-1986
Subseries: Contact Files, 1984-1987
Subseries: Petition Files, 1985-1986
Series II: Activity Files, 1984-1987
Subseries:Communication Files, 1984-1986
Subseries:Events Files, 1985-1987
Subseries: Health Survey Files, 1985
Series III: Correspondence Files, 1984-1991
Series IV: Phelps Dodge Files, 1960-1986
Subseries:General Files, 1960-1989
Subseries:Smelter Monitoring Files, 1984-1986
Subseries: Legal Files, 1984-1986
Series V: Subject Files, 1973-1989
Subseries:Copper Industry Files, 1982-1985
Subseries:Environmental Files, 1977-1989
Subseries: Health Files, 1974-1990
Subseries: Individuals, 1983-1986
Subseries: Organizations, 1983-1986
Series VI: Newspaper Clippings, 1981-1991
Series VII: Negatives, Photographs, and Slides, 1980-1986
Series VIII: Oversized Materials, 1987
Scope and Content Note
Records, 1984-1986. This collection is composed of the records of Groups Against Smelter Pollution (G.A.S.P.), including: administrative files; activity files (containing records of demonstrations, meetings, and health surveys); communication files (containing newsletters, press releases, and other G.A.S.P. writings); correspondence; newspaper clippings; negatives, photographs, and slides (containing images of smelter pollution and environmental activism); and one scrapbook. Also included are research materials regarding the Phelps Dodge Corporation, particularly documents pertaining to the legal debate on the operation of Douglas Smelter and its eventual closure. Additionally the collection includes subject files on topics of particular interest to this environmental coalition, such as health and environmental issues relating to smelter pollution, and individuals and organizations related to the smelter debate. Please note that dates listed reflect the subject content of the material.
Access Terms
Air Pollution -- Arizona.
Copper mines and mining -- Arizona.
Environmental protection -- Arizona -- Citizen participation.
Green movement -- United States.
Smelting -- Environmental aspects -- Arizona.
Smelting -- Environmental aspects -- Mexico.
Cochise County (Ariz.)
Douglas – Arizona – Economic Conditions
Groups Against Smelter Pollution (G.A.S.P.)
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 1984-1987
  .75 Linear Feet (Approximately 1,200 Items)
  Arrangement: Alphabetical
  The Administrative Files Series is divided into four subseries. Subseries: Organizational History (1985), contains letterhead and business cards, G.A.S.P. statements of mission and purpose, and promotional materials such as stickers, buttons, and posters. Subseries: Financial Files (1984-1986), contains records of public contributions, records of G.A.S.P. expenses (invoices and receipts), and bank statements. Subseries: Contact Files (1984-1987), contains business cards, mailing lists (for members and organizational contacts), and phone lists. Subseries: Petition Files (1985-1986), contains blank petition forms and records of the three major petitions circulated by G.A.S.P.
  - Subseries:Organizational History
    - Letterhead. 1985. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mission. 1985,undated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Promotional Materials. undated. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries:Financial Files
    - Bank Statements. 1984-1986. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Contributions. 1984-1986. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fundraising. 1984-1986. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Invoices. 1984-1986. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Receipts. circa 1980s. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries:Contact Files
    - Business Cards. undated. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Government Contacts. 1985-1986. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Mailing Lists. circa 1984-1987. (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
    - Media Contacts. undated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Schools and Organizations. 1984,undated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries:Petition Files
    - Blank Petitions. undated. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General Petition. undated. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Nonferrous Smelter Order Petition. 1986. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Operating Permit Petition. 1986. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Activity Files, 1984-1987
  .25 Linear Feet (about 375 Items)
  The Activity Files Series is divided into three subseries. Subseries: Communication Files (1984-1986), contains organizational newsletters, public action alerts, Mexican publications, general statements written by G.A.S.P. members, press statements and notes and memoranda. Subseries: Events Files (1985-1987), contains announcements and minutes from meetings and hearings, clippings and publicity regarding G.A.S.P. sponsored demonstrations, and a video of the 1986 "Die-In" smelter protest. Subseries: Health Survey Files (1985), contains records of a respiratory survey, asthmatic registry, and air particulate sampling study conducted by G.A.S.P. in conjunction with Dr. Andrew Slaski.
  - Subseries:Communication Files
    - Action Alerts. 1985, undated. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - General Statements. 1985, undated. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Mexico--General Communications. 1984, undated. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Newsletter. 1984-1986. (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
    - Notes and Memoranda. 1985,undated. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Press Statements. 1985-1986. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subseries:Events Files
    - Announcements. 1986-1987,undated. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Demonstrations. 1985-1986. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Die-In" Protest Video. 1986. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Meetings. 1985-1986. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Subseries:Health Survey Files
    - Respiratory Survey. 1985. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Slaski Study. 1985. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series 3: Correspondence Files, 1984-1987
  This bulk of this series contains general correspondence between G.A.S.P. members and various parties. Additionally there are separate groups of correspondence between Arizona Department of Health Services, the Environmental Protection Agency, and other state and federal legislators. There is also a folder of letters written by Palominas Public School Children to the Environmental Protection Agency after viewing a G.A.S.P. presentation on smelter pollution.
  - Arizona Department of Health Services. 1984-1986. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Children. 1985. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Protection Agency. 1984-1986. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General. 1984-1991. (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Legislative. 1984-1986. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Phelps Dodge Files, 1984-1987
  1 Linear Foot (about 1,300 items)
  The Phelps Dodge Series is divided into three subseries. Subseries: General Files (1960-1989), contains general information on the Phelps Dodge Corporation including financial reports, newspaper clippings, company publications, and detailed information on Phelps Dodge smelters and smelter closures. Subseries: Smelter Monitoring Files (1984-1986), contains Arizona Department of Health Services monitoring, Environmental Protection Agency notices of violation, as well as citizen complaints to Arizona Department of Health Services regarding Phelps Dodge smelter pollution. Subseries: Legal Files (1984-1986), contains records of various legal proceedings pertaining to Phelps Dodge operating permit applications, including related correspondence and the deposition of G.A.S.P. member Cathé Fish before the Arizona State Air Pollution Control Hearing Board.
  - Subseries:General Files
    - Financial Reports. 1984-1985. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings. 1972-1986. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Publications. 1985-1989. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Smelter--Information. 1960-1985. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Smelter Closure--Economics. 1985-1986. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Subseries:Smelter Monitoring Files
    - Air. 1984-1986. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Citizen Complaints. 1985-1986. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - SO2 Peak/ Mean Ratios. 1985. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Water. 1984-1985. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries:Legal Files
    - Consent Decree. 1986. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Consent Decree--Comments. 1986. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Deposition of Cathé Fish. 1985. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Nonferrous Smelter Order. 1985-1986. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Operating Permits. 1984-1985. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Operating Permit Denial. 1986. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Operating Permit Hearings. 1985-1986. (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Operating Permit Hearings--Comments. 1985. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series 5: Subject Files, 1960-1989
  3.25 Linear Feet (about 4,825 items)
  The Subject Files Series contains a mixture of materials including publications, government documents, research reports, promotional materials, clippings, and correspondence, relating to a variety of subject areas of interest to the G.A.S.P. membership. The files were created by G.A.S.P. members as an open resource for citizens of Bisbee to educate themselves on air pollution and smelter operation issues, although some files were added during the arrangement of the collection. This series is divided into five subseries: Subseries: Copper Industry Files (1982-1985), Subseries: Environmental Files (1977-1989), Subseries: Health Files (1974-1990), Subseries: Individuals (1983-1986), and Subseries: Organizations (1983-1986).
  - Subseries:Copper Industry Files
    - Bunker Hill Mine--Video. 1985. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - General. 1985. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Magma Copper Company. 1985. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Mexico. 1980-1985. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subseries:Environmental Files
    - Acid Rain--Canada. 1980-1986. (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Acid Rain--Clippings. 1979-1986,undated. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Acid Rain--Legislation. 1983-1985,undated. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Acid Rain--Publications. 1984-1988,undated. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Acid Rain--Reports. 1978-1985,undated. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Acid Rain--Reports. 1978-1985,undated. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Air Pollition. 1978-1987,undated. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Air Pollution--Control. 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Air Pollution--Economics. 1985,undated. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Air Quality Monitoring. 1983-1985,undated. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Atmospheric Visibility. 1979-1984. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Clean Air Act. 1977-1985. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Clean Air Act. 1977-1985. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Exxon Valdez Oil Spill. 1989. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - National Ambient Air Quality Standards. 1986. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Pollution and Agriculture. 1973-1984,undated. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sulfur Dioxide. 1980-1985. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Toxic Release Control Act. 1985. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Water Pollution. 1979-1985,undated. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Water Quality Standards. 1985-1987,undated. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Subseries:Health Files
    - Arsenic Exposure. 1974-1986,undated. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Asthma. 1980-1986. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Birth Defects. 1981-1986. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Cadmium Exposure. 1978-1985. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Cancer. 1977-1985. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Lead/Arsenic Study. 1985-1987. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Occupational Safety. 1985,undated. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Pseudo Croup. 1984. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Respiratory Studies. 1974-1985,undated. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Toxics and Hazardous Chemicals Exposure. 1979-1990. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Subseries:Individuals
    - Abbott, John. 1984. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Babbitt, Bruce. 1984-1986. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - DeConcini, Dennis. 1983-1986. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Gregory, Michael. 1983-1985,undated. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Kamp, Richard 1983-1986. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Kolbe, Jim. 1983-1986. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Udall, Morris. 1985. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Subseries:Organizations
    - American Lung Association. 1983-1985. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Arizona Clean Air Coalition. 1985. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Earth First! 1984-1986. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Environmental Defense Fund. 1985,undated. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Environmental Protection Agency. 1985-1986. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Green Action Environmental Communications Network. 1985-1986. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Greenpeace. 1984-1985. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Project Lighthawk. 1985,undated. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Sierra Club. 1985. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Southwest Environmental Service. 1984-1986. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - United Steelworkers of America. 1984-1985. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Series 6: Newspaper Clippings, 1981-1991
  .25 Linear Feet (about 375 items)
  The Newspaper Clippings Series contains clippings regarding G.A.S.P. activities and demonstrations and more generally the smelter pollution issue in the Southwest and related environmental issues. There are a small number of Spanish and German language clippings from Mexican and German publications.
  - General. undated. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - General. 1981-1991. (Box 11, Folder 9-11)
  - General (Spanish and German). 1984-1985. (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Series 7: Negatives, Photographs, and Slides, 1980-1985
  .25 Linear Feet (About 450 Items)
  The Negatives, Photographs, and Slides Series contains materials in these three formats chronicling G.A.S.P. activism and smelter pollution in Southeastern Arizona and Sonara, Mexico. Also included are three slideshows used for G.A.S.P. presentations.
  - Miscellaneous. undated. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Negatives--Smelter Pollution. undated. (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Photographs--Demonstrations. 1985,undated. (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Photographs--Smelter Pollution. 1984-1985,undated. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Slides--Cananea and Nacozari Smelters. 1983-1986. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Slides--Smelter Pollution. 1984-1985. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Slideshow--Environmental Defense Fund. undated. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Slideshow--Cathé Fish. 1980-1985. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Slideshow--Groups Against Smelter Pollution. undated. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series 8: Oversized Materials, 1987
  Two Linear Feet (one item)
  The Oversized Materials Series contains one scrapbook containing photographs, clippings, publications and other items commemorating the activities of G.A.S.P.
  - Scrapbook. 1987. (Box 13)